Today's דף Daf is נ"ב, Nun Bet, 52. We continue in the
סוגיות Sugyot related to the בור Bor and try to make it
not too boring, ha ha, sorry רבי טוב. Rebbe Tov. Anyway, we
pick up at the bottom of נ"א עמוד ב' Nun Aleph Amud
Bet and we are dealing with the issue with the משנה Mishnah
said, if the first guy passes over the well, the בור, Bor,
the pit and doesn't cover it and then the second guy doesn't
cover it, our version in the משנה Mishnah said the second guy
is חייב, Chayav, others' version said the first guy is חייב. Chayav.
But either way, the גמרא Gemara wants to know, like if they
really just both passed by and neither does anything then each one
is negligent, so they should both be liable. So the גמרא Gemara
has to set up the scenario where the first guy can pass
over the liability to the second guy of the משנה, Mishnah, that
his liability ends. So the גמרא Gemara says two versions, either that
the second guy came and started using it and that was enough
to implicitly make the second guy responsible, or the second guy used
it and the first guy gave over the cover of the well,
and that clearly made it was a handing over of responsibility. So
the גמרא Gemara now is going to turn to what that debate
is about. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like
this.
כתנאי, Ke-tannai, we'll pick up there. It is 5, 8, 11 lines
from the bottom, line that starts with the word וחד. Ve-chad. וחד
אמר אם שלו דליהב, Ve-chad amar im shelo delyahav, the one says
when you leave the second guy using it, the other one says
when you leave, when you hand over the cover to the second
guy, כתנאי, Ke-tannai, and this parallels a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. המדלה
מים מן הבור, Hamidleh mayim min habor, somebody is drawing water from
the well, ובא חברו ואמר לו, Uva chavayro ve’amar lo, and the
friend says to him, הנח לי ואני אדלה, Hanach li va’ani edleh,
you know, let me take over drawing the water, מים. Mayim. כיון
שהניחו משתמש, Kivan she'hinnicho mishtamesh,
once he left the second guy using the well, פטור, Patur, the
first guy is exempt, he renounced any responsibility, he like you know,
passes off any responsibility. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר אם שלו דליהב.
Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov omer im shelo delyahav. No,
it's not enough to leave the second guy using it, you're still
responsible, you have to wait around and cover it up yourself or
whatever together with the second guy, or but if the only time
you'll be exempt is if you explicitly or directly hand over the
cover to the second guy, that is a handing over of responsibility.
Okay, במה קמיפלגי, B’mai kamipalgi, what's this debate about? So can somebody
get that? I'm sorry. במה קמיפלגי. B’mai kamipalgi. Yeah, there's no longer
a button on the inside, so you have to,
it won't open, it won't open.
There's
a recently installed... Okay, so במה קמיפלגי, B’mai kamipalgi, what's the debate
about? Is it doing it? All
right, hopefully they'll be here by then soon enough.
Okay, במה קמיפלגי, B’mai kamipalgi, where are we up to?
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב סבר יש ברירה, Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov savar
yesh breira, היי מדידי קממלא והיי מדידי קממלא. hai mi-didi kamalleh ve-hai
mi-didi kamalleh. So רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov says
there's ברירה, breira, which means I am using the well, so we
both jointly own the well, me and Michael here. Well, when I'm
using it,
am I using Michael's part of the well when I'm using it,
or no, when I'm using it, I'm only using my part of
the well and when Michael's using it, he's only using his part
of the well.
Well, I mean when I'm using it I'm using both parts, I'm
using mine and Michael's, because you can't distinguish whose is whose, that's
the natural thing to say if you say אין ברירה. ein breira.
Or do you say יש ברירה, yesh breira, which means that no,
when I used it, I was using sort of my half of
it and when Michael uses it, he uses his half of it.
So if you want to sort of state it more specifically, I
drew the water that was mine and he drew the water that
was his. Okay, but it wasn't that we were sort of both
always jointly drawing on, using like you know something that was both
of ours. So if you say why should that matter? If you
say יש ברירה, yesh breira, which is maybe a strange idea but
if you, and particularly in this context, then that means that when
I left Michael, I was first using it, I was only using
my half. I left Michael, he was using his half. He never
was using my half, so I never, there was nothing that ever
made him take over responsibility for my half. When he used it,
he used the parts that he had rights to, but I never,
he never took over, he was never accessing the part that was
mine. So therefore I don't get out of my responsibility, only if
I explicitly hand over the cover, you know, then that is the
statement of here you be responsible for covering the well.
Well then you'll be responsible for
half, so he fell into Michael's half.
No, well that's no, the ברירה breira comes to the act of
using, when the animal falls in, the animal isn't deciding which half
and that would be shared that responsibility. When he uses it, then
we would say he's accessing his half. All right, so anyway, so
it says, all right, so מר סבר היי מדידי קממלא והיי מדידי
קממלא mar savar hai mi-didi kamalleh ve-hai mi-didi kamalleh and therefore it's
only, it only becomes Michael's full responsibility when I hand over the
cover. ורבנן סברי אין ברירה. ve-Rabbanan savri ein breira. No, there's no
way of distinguishing, so when Michael's using it, he's using both of
our halves, and therefore he is. taking responsibility for the well. אמר
רבינא Amar Ravina ואזדו לטעמייהו, v'azdu l'taamayhu, so actually this debate here
about watching a well, it's a perfect explanation what you just gave
in and parallels another debate that the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov have, דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in
the mishna, השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה, hashutfim shenadru hana'ah ze mize,
if you have me and Michael here where we're partners in this
field, and we got really annoyed at one another, so we each
took a vow that I took a vow he couldn't get any
benefit from me, a נדר neder made my half of my property
forbidden to him, he made his property forbidden to me, that's a
very good attitude right as we're going into the three weeks, שנאת
חינם, sinat chinam, okay, trying to do a little תיקון tikun of
that. So, we were נודרו הנאה זה מזה, nodru hana'ah ze mize,
אסורים להכנס לחצר, asurim lehikanes l'chatzer, we can't go into our jointly
held field, because I will be benefiting from his half of the
field. Okay, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer,
no, זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו. ze nichnas l'toch
shelo v'ze nichnas l'toch shelo. When I go into the yard, I'm
using the half of the yard that's mine, and when he goes
into the yard, he's using the half of the yard that's his.
It's not that there's a line down it, we're using the exact
same part of land, okay, but nevertheless we say I'm accessing my
rights and he's accessing his rights and we're never actually using the
ownership or the parts, the rights of the person that owns the
other half. All right, so that's exactly it, when you use something
that is being that is owned jointly, to what degree are you
using something that belongs to the other person or are you just
accessing the part that you have rights to.
Okay, במאי קמיפלגי, B'mai kamifligi, what's the debate? רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
סבר יש ברירה, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov savar yesh breirah, there's
it determines it's like how you act determines what you know sort
of what was happening, האי לדינפשיה עייל והאי לדינפשיה עייל, hai l'dinafshai
ayeil v'hai l'dinafshai ayeil, every person every time you're using it you're
accessing only your rights and not the other person's rights, your property
and not the other person's, and therefore you're not violating the נדר.
neder. ורבנן סברי אין ברירה v'Rabbanan savri ein breirah and the rabbis
say there isn't ברירה. breirah. Fine. Okay. And that's determined by this
well as well, well this well as well, there's well additionally, I
really have none of that on purpose, whether the using of it
is the full taking over of it, or do you have to
hand over the cover to implicitly be giving over responsibility.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, המוכר בור לחברו, hamocher bor l'chavero,
now since we're talking about handing over the cover as a way
of handing over responsibility, we're going to talk about it as an
act of קנין. kinyan. המוכר בור לחברו, hamocher bor l'chavero, you're selling
a well to somebody, כיון שמסר לו דליו, keivan shemasar lo dalyav,
when he hands over again we're going to interpret this as cover,
although again I agree with Michael that the simple meaning of this
is the bucket, when you hand over the cover, קנה, kana, the
other person takes possession. So now this is and I will just
warn you that we're going to do a series of statements here
which make it sound like a new type of קנין kinyan which
we're not familiar with. Normally the way you take possession of property,
it's כסף, שטר, או חזקה. kesef, shtar, o chazakah. But there are
some times where you can hand over something which symbolically is giving
over, you know, sort of giving over the keys to the kingdom,
right, you know, which is a symbolically of giving over the thing
that controls it. Like if I give you over the keys to
the car, did you do a משיכה meshichah on the car, הגבהה
hagbahah on the car? Like no, but symbolically I have given you
the thing that allows you to control and access, right, that piece
of property. So it seems like there so classic example is giving
over the keys to the house or the cover to the well,
right. So it's going to seem like that there were some early
statements that that would be a type of a קנין. kinyan. But
the גמרא Gemara pushes back on that. The גמרא Gemara doesn't like
it because that doesn't I don't know, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't
like it and maybe it would have just been a type of
a like a you know, a like a גמירות דעת, gmirot da'at,
right, like it would have fallen into some generic category of things
that have been established as norms even if you know they don't
fall into a formal definition. But anyway but the גמרא Gemara pushes
back on that and the גמרא Gemara redefines all of these statements
to not mean what they what they're sounding like they're saying. So
let's take a look. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, המוכר בור
לחברו כיון שמסר לו דליו קנה. hamocher bor l'chavero keivan shemasar lo
dalyav kana. As as soon as you hand over the cover, you
take possession. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי בכספא, ee
b'chaspa, because it's ground, land is only acquired with כסף, שטר, וחזקה.
kesef, shtar, v'chazakah. So if you paid the money, ליקני בכספא, likni
b'chaspa, the money is the act that you take possession. אי בחזקה,
ee b'chazakah, if you're doing your קנין kinyan with use, you know,
showing mastery through use, ליקני בחזקה, likni b'chazakah, let that be the
קנין. kinyan. So and it should have said if with the שטר
shtar let it be the שטר. shtar. Anyway, what's the significance of
handing over the cover? So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם בחזקה, l'olam
b'chazakah, fine, you went out and you did use it. So what's
the issue of handing over the cover? ובעי למימר ליה חזק וקני,
u'baei l'meimar lei chazek u'knei, in order for the קנין kinyan to
be effective, the act of קנין, kinyan, the seller has to say
to has to say to you, okay, go ahead, do the act
of taking possession and then you'll take and then that'll take possession,
right, he has to sort of give over the permission to do
the act of taking possession. וכיון שמסר לו
דליו, v'keivan shemasar lo dalyav, once you handed over the cover, כמאן
דאמר לו לך חזק וקני דמי, k'man d'amar lo lech chazek u'knei
dami, you don't have to say it explicitly. Giving over the cover
is saying like, okay, I am now ready for you to go
ahead and do that act of taking possession. So it's not really
the act of taking possession, it authorizes you to do the act.
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, similarly Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi said, המוכר בית לחברו, hamocher bayit l'chavero, you sell
a house to your friend, top of צ"ב עמוד א', tzadik bet
amud alef, כיון שמסר לו מפתח, keivan shemasar lo mafte'ach, if you
as long as as soon as you hand over He קנה, kana,
you take possession. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי בכספא,
Iy bechaspa, if you paid money then the money, or when you
already paid money let that be the act of possession. אי בחזקה,
Iy bechazakah, if you took a חזקה chazakah like to actually made
some improvement on the yard, you locked the door or something of
that nature. Well, right, let's say a key would be enough, okay,
okay, yeah, there you go, good point. Okay, לקני בחזקה, likni bechazakah,
let that be enough. So the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם בחזקה, le'olam
bechazakah, fine, you did some act of חזקה. chazakah. ובעי למימר ליה
לך חזק וקני, U-ba'ei leimei lei leikh chazek u-knei, but again, you
need to be authorized. וכיון שמסר לו מפתח, Ve-keivan she-masar lo mafteach,
when you gave him the key, כמאן דאמר ליה לך חזק וקני
דמי, kema'an de-amar lei leikh chazek u-knei dami, it's like you authorized
him. Okay, so again, it's pushing back against the simple sense of
these statements, which is that there's a new type of a קנין
kinyan which is handing over that thing that controls the object.
No, that is only an authorization to now let him do a
חזקה, chazakah, but the קנין kinyan is only effected through the act
of חזקה. chazakah. So we are redefining these statements to turn them
into authorizations rather than acts of קנין. kinyan. Yes.
Totally non-conceptual question. Yes.
Isn't it just too
old to realize like they had locks with keys?
Right. Well, I mean, I guess I was very familiar with that,
but yeah.
Number, locks are ancient.
There you go. Okay. How would they, I mean, you would understand
why that became a need at early on in society to protect
your objects. Yeah, I guess you could have a lot of watchdogs
or something.
Something as the car driving would be good, I mean,
it would be like a, yeah, that would be like a משיכה
meshicha or something. Okay, so אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, similarly
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says משום רבי ינאי, mishum Rabbi Yannai, המוכר
עדר לחבירו, hamocher eder le-chavero,
you're selling a flock to your friend. כיון שמסר לו משכוכית, Keivan
she-masar lo mashchuchis, as soon as you hand over the משכוכית, mashchuchis,
קנה, kana, you take possession. Now we'll see in a minute what
the משכוכית mashchuchis is, but it has the word משוך, mashoch, it's
something that causes the flock to be led and to follow you.
Okay, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? So, okay,
but big deal, what does that do anything? אי במשיכה, Iy bi-meshicha,
if you actually made the flock move, you pulled them physically or
through leading them, לקני במשיכה, likni bi-meshicha, let that be the act.
אי במסירה, Iy bi-mesirah, if you did through like handing over the
reins, so לקני במסירה. likni bi-mesirah. Now the reins actually sound similar
to this, but the מסירה mesirah is as it's connected to the
animal. If you like hand over the reins of the horse when
it's on the horse, that's seen as like you're taking possession, you're
taking hold of the horse. Okay, which is not what we're talking
about here. Here we're talking about
no, but that's why. מסירה Mesirah maybe is an idea that gets
close to this, but מסירה mesirah works only when it's attached to
the animal. So then you're, but that's not a category we know
yet. The only category we know is actually physically moving the animal
or holding on to something that's attached to the animal, but it's
directly connected to the object itself. This is something that is not
connected to the object. So we don't know, that's not a category
that we have.
Yeah, no, but what I meant is handing him the object
the way he hands him. Right, so it's conceptually similar to מסירה,
mesirah, but the difference is that this is purely symbolic, מסירה mesirah
is at least connected to the animal. לעולם במשיכה, Le'olam bi-meshicha, fine,
really you're going to do the קנין kinyan through moving the animals.
But ובעי למימר ליה לך משוך וקני, u-ba'ei leimei lei leikh meshokh
u-knei, you have to authorize him to do that. וכיון שמסר לו
משכוכית, Ve-keivan she-masar lo mashchuchis, and now that you've given him whatever
this משכוכית mashchuchis thing is, כמאן דאמר ליה לך משוך וקני דמי,
kema'an de-amar lei leikh meshokh u-knei dami, it's like you've already given
him the authorization. So again, pushing back on all of these statements
and saying they don't mean it, they're not really the act of
קנין, kinyan, they're just the authorization to do a traditional act of
קנין. kinyan. Now the גמרא Gemara says, מאי משכוכית? Mai mashchuchis? What
is this משכוכית? mashchuchis? הכא תרגימו קקשתא, Hacha targimu kekashta,
here they translated it as a bell. You ring a bell that
causes the sheep to follow. רבי יעקב אומר, Rabbi Yaakov omer, עיזא
דאזלא בריש עדרא. izza de-azla be-reish idra. No,
it's like the
right, the alpha goat, exactly. The goat that goes at the head
of the flock, it's sort of like a sheepdog, and all the
animals follow it. כדדרשה
ההוא גלילאה, Ki-derashah hu gelilah, like a certain Galilean explicated or gave
a דרשה derashah sermonized, קמיה דרב חסדא, kamih d'Rav Chisda,
in front of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. כד רגיז רעיא, Kad ragiz
ra'aya, when the shepherd gets mad על ענא, al ana, on the
flock, עביד לנגדא סמותא, avid li-negda samutsa,
it makes the leader, the head goat, blind. So if God wants
to punish בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael for sins, it punishes the leaders
is the point. Okay, by the way, תוספות Tosafot deals with the
fact that number one, in בבא בתרא Bava Batra the רשב"ם Rashbam
actually seems to be saying the simple reading of this גמרא, Gemara,
that actually handing over keys to a house could be a form
of קנין. kinyan. So תוספות's Tosafot got a problem with that because
of the conclusion of this גמרא, Gemara, but it's interesting that the
רשב"ם Rashbam seems to actually embrace that as a real possibility. There's
also a סוגיא sugya in the beginning of פסחים Pesachim though, which
is when do you have a responsibility to do בדיקת חמץ bedikat
chametz if you're renting out your house? And the גמרא Gemara there
speaks about has the renter handed over the keys or not? But
תוספות Tosafot says that is not about the קנין, kinyan, the owner.
Thank you, the right, the owner. Right, right. I meant the one
renting, but you're correct. Oh, right, yes, you're right. The owner.
I was just doing a translation of משכיר. maskir. Anyway, has the
owner... Has the owner handed over the keys or not? So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* says that is not about whether you actually the... the
rent... when does the rental period begin, like when have you done
the קנין *kinyan* on renting the place, but that's the simple point
that you cannot obligate somebody to check their house for חמץ *chametz*
if they don't have access to the house yet. Okay, so there
he says that there is a place where handing over the keys
is significant, but that's in an area of הלכה Halacha *halacha* where
the issue is having practical access. But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, you know,
but again, it is worth noting that A, another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
speaks also about handing over the keys, and B, that the רשב״ם
*Rashbam* at least in one place actually speaks about this as a
type of a קנין *kinyan*, against the way the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
translated this to all just be about authorization.
Could it work the other way around? Like let's say my lease
is up but you know I still have the keys, I haven't
given them back to the owner, of course he's obligated to check.
Interesting, probably. I mean that might be, that could very well be,
but I don't know.
Okay. So we noted it's the goat, right? What? We noted it's
the goat.
Yeah, so your point being what?
Point being that's what shepherds do, they have
sheep lead. Right.
Oh, I see.
So the goat, as is still done today, the goat is valuable
because it acts as the leader of sheep.
I see. Sort of like the idea of a sheep dog, so
you're not having a sheep leading sheep, you're having a different type
of animal. You're having a goat leading the sheep, right.
That's what goats do.
Right. Okay, very good. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Who's that?
Is that one of the maintenance guys? Okay, we'll just climb up
the window if we can. Okay, let's go on. Next משנה Mishnah.
*mishna*. Okay, next משנה Mishnah *mishna*. כיסהו הראשון ובא שני ומצאו מגולה
*Kisahu harishon uva sheini umetzau meguleh* ולא כיסה *Velo kisa*. So we're
back to the first and the second guy. Which guy is obligated?
So the first one covered it. And then the second guy came
and somehow it's got uncovered in the interim. השני חייב chayav, *Hasheini
chayav*. So now the second guy, the first guy did his responsibility,
so now and the second guy who's also the owner, now sees
that it's exposed, so that becomes now fully the second guy's responsibility.
I mean, נעבעך *nebech*, he saw it, but okay. So the גמרא׳ס
*Gemara's* going to ask at what stage does the first one become
responsible again? Like when he becomes aware that it's been exposed, or
should he, does he have to, you know, does he have to
keep tabs on it? You know, if he could become aware that
it was exposed, is that enough? All right, but here we're not
dealing with that. We're saying that the second guy saw it, so
the second guy becomes responsible.
Does he have to prove that he, the first guy, that he
actually covered it? Because then they're like, "Oh yeah, I covered it,"
and you know...
Yeah, you know, that's an excellent question, which I remember I was
once learning with, you know, חיים *Chaim* Saiman, who's a legal scholar,
whatever, also you know, serious תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*. Anyway, and he
was pointing out to me how you know half of the law,
cases in law, are not about like what the law is, but
about like how do you, how do you establish proof about whether
something happens or not, right? So like, you know, exactly if you
said, the questions are never asked, right? So exactly who has... I
mean they're sometimes asked, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
*hamotzi mechavero alav haraaya*, you know, and so on. But you're right,
like what level of proof does the first guy need to establish
that he did the covering? What level of proof do you have
to prove that the first guy passed over and was פטור patur,
*pattur* and all those types of questions? Yeah, those are actually excellent
questions. Okay.
But doesn't it become immaterial if the second guy doesn't cover it?
What? Doesn't it become immaterial if the second guy doesn't cover it?
No, if the first guy covered it and the second guy didn't,
the second guy saw it and didn't, then it's all the second
guy's responsibility. But the second guy's now going to want to go
back to the first guy and say "I don't believe you that
you actually covered it."
Doesn't matter, because you use it afterwards, it was
your responsibility to cover it whether you found it covered or uncovered.
First of all, you didn't use it. It says you passed by
and you saw it uncovered. Okay, so you're right. This גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* assumes that if the first guy didn't and the second guy
passed over it, that they're both responsible. The reason the first guy
is exempt is only because the first guy covered it. So רש״י
*Rashi* says this is different than the previous משנה Mishnah *mishna* because
the previous משנה Mishnah *mishna* was assuming that the second guy used
it or the second guy was handed over the cover, and that
made the second guy fully responsible. This משנה mishnah. *mishna* assumes that
if the first guy hadn't covered it, then they would share responsibility,
right? So that's true. The simple case is, first guy passes over,
doesn't cover it, second guy passes over it and doesn't cover it,
they're both equally responsible. So here the first guy's saying "I got
out of it, I covered it." So my cover went out. But
the second guy would like the first guy to be responsible together
with him. Okay, but if the first guy covered it, he does
get out of it, and then the second guy becomes responsible. Okay,
if the second guy saw it uncovered. Otherwise nobody's responsible, everybody's an
אונס ones. *oness*. Okay, השני חייב chayav. *hasheini chayav*. כיסהו כראוי k'ra'uy.
*Kisahu keraui* and if it was covered properly, ונפל לתוכו שור shor
וחמור *venafal letocho shor vechamor* and an ox or donkey fell into
it, ומת *vamet* and died, פטור patur. *pattur*, you're exempt because, you
know, you covered it. לא lo, כיסהו כראוי k'ra'uy, *Lo kisahu keraui*
if you didn't cover it properly, ונפל לתוכו שור וחמור ומת חייב
chayav, *venafal letocho shor vechamor vamet chayav*, then obviously you'd be חייב
chayav. *chayav*. So it's not just the act of covering, it has
to be a covering that was appropriate to withstand, you know,
people, animals walking over it. All right.
נפל לפניו מקולו *Nafal lefanav mikolo* now... נפלה
לפניו מקול הכרייה חייב. Naflah lefanav mikol hakariyah chayav, If the animal
fell forward because it heard somebody in the well digging and that
startled the animal and fell, then the owner of the well is
חייב, chayav, even if the person digging is not the owner of
the well. Right? Why wouldn't you sort of say why doesn't everybody
get off the hook here? The guy who was digging would say,
yeah, it fell because of me, but that's just like a גראמה
בנזיקין, grama binizikin, right? I it's not my well, so okay it
has an accident, I didn't directly damage it. And the guy who
owns the well could say, yeah it fell but that wasn't my
fault, my well didn't make it fall, like my well didn't damage
it, it fell into the well because of this other guy's digging.
But you don't say that. The actual even though it's the sound
of the digging that startled the animal, the owner of the well
is still seen as having done the damage, and it says and
therefore even though again it's not that the well all by itself
caused the animal to fall in, and the owner of the well
is חייב. chayav Okay, so נפלה לפניו מקול הכרייה חייב, chayav. ולאחריו
מקול הכרייה פטור. vel'acharaiv mikol hakariyah patur. If however the animal fell
backwards into the well because of the sound of the digging, פטור,
patur. then the owner of the well is exempt, which is pretty
interesting and we'll see why.
נפלה לתוכו שור וכליו ונשתברו, חמור וכליו ונתקרעו. Naflah letocho shor vechelav
venishtaberu, chamor vechelav venitkare'u. So this is the famous issue the issue
we've been dealing with for the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet, that
שור ולא אדם, חמור ולא כלים. Shor velo adam, chamor velo kelim.
So if the ox fell in and its vessels broke, vessels here
doesn't just mean loads it's carrying, it would mean like the yoke
or you know those types of things that are naturally on the
ox, they broke, or the donkey fell in, hey thank you, or
the donkey fell in and its saddlebags tore, that's why it uses
the word tore here because a donkey classically has saddlebags, חייב על
הבהמה פטור על הכלים. chayav al habehemah patur al hakelim. You're liable
for the animal and you're exempt for the vessels. Because that's the
standard הלכה that you're exempt for vessels in a well. נפלה לתוכו
שור וחרש שוטה וקטן. Naflah letocho shor vecheresh shoteh vekatan. Let's say
an ox that is, what? Yes. Let's say an ox that is
not owned by, but an ox that is a חרש שוטה וקטן,
cheresh shoteh vekatan, at least whatever, that's the way the גמרא Gemara
is going to translate it, okay, because then you are then you
are חייב, chayav. you are liable. בן ובת עבד ואמה, Ben ubat
eved ve'amah, if however these people that are mentioned specifically in a
different category by the what do you call it by the goring
ox, if it's right a child or a slave, then you are
פטור. patur. We don't treat them as a different category as if
a normal whatever standard person were to fall in, you're exempt by
the well you are exempt on the injury of people, right? And
the חידוש chiddush here is the חידוש chiddush of the last part
at least is that you shouldn't say the reason a well you're
exempt by people is because people should be responsible for themselves, but
maybe if it's a child maybe you should be חייב. chayav? That's
a pretty good argument. Or you don't say by a slave, well
let's just treat a slave as property and therefore it's like damaged
property. So there is actually both a חידוש chiddush of the idea
of children and slaves that they do both still fall into the
exemption of the death of people to which or to which you
are פטור. pattur Okay, we will get back of course to the
ox that is a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh vekatan. Okay, now
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So there's a lot
in this משנה. mishnah So the גמרא Gemara says ורישא עד אימת
מיפטר. verisha ad emat miftar. So the second guy he
covered it and then it got exposed and then the second guy
saw it and is חייב, chayav at what stage do we expect
the first guy to also to you know to re-ignite his responsibility?
Like at what stage can we say you should have found out
at that stage that it had been exposed and you had to
go back and do something about it? You don't remain exempt for
the rest of your life. If you had heard that it got
exposed then you become responsible again. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב בכדי שידע. Amar Rav bichedei sheyeda. He has to actually have
enough time, I mean there's different ways of reading this, I'll read
תוספות's Tosafot way. Okay, תוספות Tosfos says it's there
we can expect that he found out about it. There was enough
time for him to know about it. People were talking about it,
you would expect by now you must have got word that it
was exposed and if and I don't mean we can take it
as to your point Michael, nobody has to prove that you heard
about it, once a sufficient amount of time has passed that you
should have heard about it, you become responsible again,
to give the witness true.
Okay, maybe if you could prove that you're away then it wouldn't
be בכדי שידע. bichedei sheyeda. Given where you were and given our
normal expectations for the word to get to you, right?
Then at that stage you become חייב chayav. again. ושמואל אמר בכדי
שיודיעוהו. Ushmuel amar bichedei sheyodi'uhu. So the way this is the way
תוספות Tosfos explains this is it's not just enough time for you
to hear by the grapevine. There has to have been actually enough
time or maybe actually in fact that you were informed of it
directly. People said, oh this is Michael's well, somebody better go and
tell Michael that there's a problem with his well. Because if you
just hear rumors by the grapevine, that maybe doesn't create enough of
a sense of obligation, right, of imperative to go do something about
it. No, there has to have actually been enough time to get
the message to you, to inform you.
רבי יוחנן אמר בכדי שיודיעוהו וישכור. Rabbi Yochanan amar bichedei sheyodi'uhu veyiscor.
ויכרות ארזים ויכסנו. veyichros arazim veychasenu.
He has to have not just enough time to find out, but
he's got to have enough time to find out, hire workers, make
a new cover, and cover it up. And the חידוש chiddush here
is that what well, okay, I mean if that's literally what you
would need to cover it up, how could you be liable before
that? Before that you're an אונס. ones. And the answer is no,
before that you should hire watchers to watch it, you know, and
people to put these those those orange triangles and stand by it
until you can get the cover made. So interesting questions of like
what is your degree of responsibility, how much do you have to
have a clear knowledge that it actually is true? Yeah, I heard
reports, I didn't give them any weight. And how much do you
have to act immediately to do something or can you have the
time to actually do the best fix and you don't have to
worry about the interim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. כסהו
כראוי ונפל לתוכו שור וחמור פטור. kissahu k'ra'uy v'nafal l'tocho shor v'chamor
patur. If you covered it and then the ox or donkey fell
in then you're exempt if you covered it properly. כיון דכסהו כראוי
היכי נפל? keivan d'chissahu k'ra'uy heichi nafal? I don't get it, if
you covered it properly, how did anything happen? You know, accidents do
happen, but you know, you could have said like I don't know,
רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'einah metzuyah or something like that, but let's
see what the
גמרא Gemara says, right? So אמר רב יצחק בר בר חנה amar
Rav Yitzchak bar bar Chana שהתליע מתוכו. shehitlia mitocho. It rotted from
within, literally it became wormy from within. Right, if you knew that
it was rotting, if you put on some type of a thing
that clearly was old wood or whatever, then it's not כראוי. keraui
Or let's say you put on something that you knew could would
be good for a week, or you should have known, but then
after a week might not live for might not you know might
not stay firm after a week, then after a week you become
responsible again. So it has to have been that something happened that
from you did everything you knew you were responsible to, but then
something that happened that you could not have known about. That had
termites and there was no way presumably you could have known about
that. Okay, by the way, I guess that at one stage I
have to mention this because I keep on thinking about manhole covers.
Apparently I was told that when at IBM when they used to
interview people for a job, you know, one of the questions they
would ask them just to see how they would think would be
why are manhole covers round? So anybody have any guesses what the
proper answer is? Well if you know the answer, I always thought
it was because like a manhole is cylindrical because that's like more
efficient use of space because a person is cylindrical, so why do
you want to make a square? You know, but because you
can carry it and then you can roll it.
Oh that's interesting. Apparently the answer is there's no way you can
put a round manhole cover on incorrectly.
Right, if it's square, right, so it's
also the only shape that won't fit within its own hole. It
won't fall into its own hole.
I don't understand, that could be true about anything. What do you
mean? No, no, oh right, because because if you did right because
then you could do an angle if you did a square, right,
that's a variation of that, because if you did a square and
you put it at an angle, it would fall
in, right? Okay, anyway, so שהתליע מתוכו, shehitlia mitocho, it rotted from
within. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they asked the question: כסהו כיסוי שיכול
לעמוד לפני שוורים ואין יכול לעמוד לפני גמלים. kissahu kisui sheyachol la'amod
lifnei shevarim v'ein yachol la'amod lifnei gemalim. Let's say you put a
cover on that could withstand oxen but not withstand camels. ואתו גמלים
וארעוהו v'asu gemalim v'aru'uhu and camels walked over it and weakened it,
ואתו שוורים ונפלו ביה v'asu shevarim v'naflu bei and then oxen walked
on it and they fell into it because now it had been
weakened. מאי, mai, are you liable or not? So the גמרא Gemara
says היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דשכיחי גמלים, ei
d'shchichi gemalim, if it's an area in which camels are common, פושע
הוא, poshea hu, then it's a negligent, then you should know, a
cover that can't withstand camels in a place of camels are present
is not a good cover because I can expect that there will
be camels and it'll get weakened and then oxen will fall. Okay,
so פושע הוא. poshea hu.
ואי דלא שכיחי גמלים, v'ei d'lo shchichi gemalim, if it's a place
that you normally shouldn't expect camels, אנוס הוא, anus hu, then you
did do everything you should do, you didn't had no need to
expect that there would be camels. לא צריכא דאתו לפרקים, lo tzricha
d'asu l'prakim, occasionally camels come. מי אמרינן כיון דאתו לפרקים mi amrinan
keivan d'asu l'prakim since they occasionally come פושע הוא, poshea hu, you're
negligent, דאיבעי ליה אסקיה אדעתיה d'iba'ei lei asukei ada'atei you should have
anticipated that it'll eventually happen. או דלמא אמרינן כיון דהשתא ליתנהו, o
dilma amrinan keivan d'hashta leitnehu, they're not here now and you don't
have to sort of anticipate, you know,
unusual occurrences even if they do happen occasionally, so then אנוס הוא,
anus hu, you're an אונס. ones. Now I do have to tell
you that I don't really, I mean I do understand the question,
but I don't understand why it's different than any other question of
what constitutes כראוי, k'rauy. because normally, right, the גמרא Gemara has a
concept of like a רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah and a רוח שאינה
מצויה ruach she'einah metzuyah and degrees of how common something is. So
you know, let's say you said, I mean let's you know, if
camels never come, then that's like a total רוח שאינה מצויה ruach
she'einah metzuyah that's in the category of אונס. oness, If they sometimes
come, you know, that's somewhere between רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah and רוח
שאינה מצויה, ruach she'einah metzuyah, right? I mean so like in any
type of a question of how good of a cover, it's how
much do you have to anticipate, you know, possible occurrences that are
not common but happen eventually. I mean maybe that is just what
the גמרא Gemara is saying except since they're talking about a cover
and we're not talking about a fence, rather than talking about a
רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah and רוח שאינה מצויה, ruach she'einah metzuyah, we're
talking about גמלים מצויה gemalim metzuyah and גמלים שאינם מצויה. gemalim she'einam
metzuyah. But it's just a question of like what is the degree
of שמירה shmira that is needed. Yes.
I get we're talking about a type of בור bor which is
like a heap of something or a package. Right, we're talking about
actual בורות borot that are cisterns. There's something basic that's fundamental I
don't get. Like people would own בורות borot in רשות הרבים? reshut
harabbim? Like why? Well, right.
I mean I don't know, I mean if that I don't you're
right like normally I mean the assumption is you shouldn't have been
doing it but you can get out of a liability if you
covered it. But the other possibility is we're talking about a בור
bor in your רשות reshut that's at the edge for רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. So it's one or the other. But right if we're
talking about a בור bor in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim then it's
true we're going around this whole conversation about covering to get exempt
from responsibility in a context where you really weren't allowed to have
been doing it in the first place. Clarify that. Right. Right. Yeah.
הלל? Hillel?
I don't know is it is it comparable to the רוח מצויה
ruach metzuya because the question here is if the גמל gamal weakens
it and the שור falls in. Right. Not if the גמל gamal
weakens it and the גמל gamal falls in.
No, I understand. But I'm just looking at the גמל gamal as
a type of a רוח. ruach. Like if I made a fence
in front of my cow
and my ox, right? And then some type a very unexpected wind
that would knock down the fence, I don't have to be concerned
about. A common wind that would I would. Something that's in the
middle, that's the question. So I just see the camel as a
type of a wind that's blowing down my cover.
It's indirect because the camel's not blowing it down. The camel's just
weakening it and something smaller is falling in which is even more
removed from a direct relationship. Maybe. Right.
Because it would be I still don't exactly see it and if
an uncommon wind came and it weakened the fence enough that now
my ox could break through the fence... I don't know, to me
it seems like a very much parallel. And I just want to
remind everybody that we have like we tend to have three levels,
right? We tend to have
פושע, poshea, אונס, oness right? So this is like this is considered
like a רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, right? This is a normal level
of שמירה. shmira. This is like, שמירה פחותה, shmira pechuta, right? And
then you've got this whole thing, right? Then you've got this whole
thing called like if it was שומרים shomrim you'd have this thing
called גניבה ואבידה, gneiva va'aveida, right? So if you did a שמירה
מעולה, shmira me'ula, right? You're protecting it against גניבה ואבידה gneiva va'aveida
and anything
higher is considered a רוח שאינה מצויה, ruach she'eina metzuya, right?
Right? An אונס oness is a רוח שאינה מצויה, ruach she'eina metzuya,
right? To start. But let's say you did something that was enough
to protect it from a רוח, ruach, if you did enough to
stop, anyway, whatever, there's three levels. So normally to me this whole
question, if only the most אונס oness can happen then obviously you
did it so much that only an אונס oness. could happen obviously
you're exempt, right? And if you did it less from something that's
very common obviously you're a פושע. poshea. But if you did it
enough to whatever, there's always that middle category that you want to
be asking about. Yes.
The טבע teva has changed today. Bovines are larger than camels.
Oh, really? That's very interesting. Okay, so anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. Middle level likelihood of camels coming and they might come sometime
in the future. It's not impossible but it's not common. Okay, are
you going to be responsible? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this:
תיקו דאתו פירקי. Teyku d'atu pirkei. מי אמרינן כיון דאתו לפירקי פושע
הוא דאיבעי ליה אסקיה אדעתיה? Mi amrinan keivan d'atu lepirkei poshea hu
de'ibei lei asukei ada'atei? It should have occurred to you.
או דילמא כיון דהשתא מיהת ליכא אונס הוא? o dilma keivan dehashta
mihat leika oness hu? Then you have no responsibility for them and
as long as you addressed the immediate present concerns and this is
not a likely thing you don't have to worry about it. תא
שמע Ta shma come and hear. כיסהו כראוי ונפל לתוכו שור או
חמור פטור. Kisehu keraui venafal letocho shor o chamor patur. You covered
it properly and then you're פטור. pattur, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's
the case?
אילימא כראוי לשוורים וכראוי לגמלים היכי נפל? Ilima keraui leshvarim vekeraui legemalim
heichi nafal? How did anything happen? We're ignoring the answer we gave
before about that it rotted. אלא לאו כראוי לשוורים ולא כראוי לגמלים?
Ela lav keraui leshvarim velo keraui legemalim? It must be that the
חידוש chiddush in the משנה mishnah is that it was כראוי k'rauy
but not a hundred percent. It was good for oxen but it
was not good enough for camels.
ואי דשכיחי גמלים אמאי פטור פושע הוא? Ve'i deshchichi gemalim amai patur
poshea hu? Then you shouldn't be exempt. You're negligent. ואי דלא שכיחי
גמלים פשיטא אונס הוא? Ve'i delo shchichi gemalim pishita oness hu? And
if they're not prevalent, obviously you're exempt. אלא לאו דאתו לפירקי דאזלו
גמלים וארעוהו ואתו שוורים ונפלו ביה? Ela lav de'atu lepirkei de'azlu gemalim
ve'aruhu ve'atu shvarim venaplu bei? For the משנה mishnah to be a
חידוש, chiddush, like what's the חידוש? chiddush? What's the case that you
covered it properly and how did something happen and then why are
you exempt? So the only way to explain it is דאתו לפירקי
de'atu lepirkei camels would occasionally come, דאזלו גמלים וארעוהו ואתו שוורים ונפלו
ביה de'azlu gemalim ve'aruhu ve'atu shvarim venaplu bei and they came and
they weakened and then oxen came so that's how even though you
did a good job an ox fell in because camels weakened it.
והחידוש Vehechiddush is that you're exempt because even though it wasn't a
hundred percent because even though camels would come occasionally you did what
you needed to do.
וקתני פטור אלמא כיון דהשתא ליכא אונס הוא? Uktani patur alma keivan
dehashta leika oness hu? You're exempt. You're an אונס. onnes. So you
see that's a good way of explaining the context of the משנה
mishnah where some Something could have happened; you did what you needed
to and nevertheless the animal fell in and nevertheless you're פטור pattur,
because it was a camel that came and that was a case
that was not שכיח. shachiah. אמר ליה לא, Amar lei lo, לעולם
כרבי לשור וכרבי לגמל. le'olam k'Rabbi l'shor u'k'Rabbi l'gamal. No, the case
would be that you did a completely good one both for ox
and camels. וכי חסא היכי נפלה? V'chi chasa heichi nafla? You want
to know how did it fall in? אמר רב יצחק בר בר
חנה, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar bar Chana, שנתליה מתוכה, shnitlia mitocha, it
rotted from within. Again, the גמרא Gemara could have said פשיטא, peshita,
but alright, anyway. So we're back to that. If it's rotted from
within, so it's not relevant for our question. תא שמע. Ta shema.
So now we're going to try to say the exact same thing
in the opposite direction from the second case of the משנה. mishnah
לא כסהו כראוי Lo kissahu k'rauy ונפל לתוכו שור או חמור, v'nafal
l'tocho shor o chamor,
you didn't cover it properly and the animal died, חייב. chayav. היכי
דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא לא כראוי לשור ולא כראוי
לגמל, Ileima lo k'rauy l'shor v'lo k'rauy l'gamal, if you really didn't
do anything that was sufficient from any measure, פשיטא, peshita, obviously you're
חייב. chayav? צריכא למימר Tzaricha l'meimar you're חייב? chayav. Of course you're
חייב chayav, if you really didn't cover it. אלא לאו, Ela lav,
כראוי לשור ולא כראוי לגמל. k'rauy l'shor v'lo k'rauy l'gamal. The חידוש
chidush is that you did something which was a minimal type of
a covering. It was good for ox and not good for camels,
and you would think, oh, at least I covered it. And the
משנה mishnah is telling you that is not כראוי. k'rauy, Okay, היכי
דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי דשכיחי גמלים, Ei d'shchichi gamalim,
if camels are prevalent, פושע הוא, poshea hu, obviously that's not כראוי
k'rauy and we're back to our point that the משנה mishnah is
obvious. ואי דלא שכיחי גמלים, V'ei d'lo shchichi gamalim, and if they're
not prevalent, אנוס הוא, anus hu, then you actually should be exempt.
אלא לאו, Ela lav, must be our case, דאתו לפרקים, d'atu l'prakim,
they come occasionally, בדקא דאתו גמלים וארעו ואתו שור ונפלו בה, badka
d'atu gamalim v'aru v'atu shor v'naflu bah, the camels came and they
weakened it and the oxen came and they fell in. וקתני חייב,
U'katni chayav, you're חייב. chayav. So again, we wanted to say that
was the initial case in the משנה mishnah that you're פטור, Patur,
now we're saying this is the case in the משנה mishnah that
you're חייב. chayav. It says you did it כראוי, k'rauy. you did
it שלא כראוי, shelo k'rauy, but if you really were irresponsible it's
obvious. So it doesn't mean you were totally irresponsible, it means it
was not fully כראוי k'rauy. because you did not protect it against
camels, and camels were somewhat to be expected. They weren't שכיח, shachiah,
but they occasionally came and that's not fully כראוי. אלמא כיון דאתו
לפרקים, Alma keivan d'atu l'prakim, you see that since camels come occasionally,
פושע הוא, poshea hu, the משנה mishnah. is telling you that's not
fully appropriate, that's not fully כראוי. דאיבעי ליה אסקיה אדעתיה, Deibei lei
askei adaiteih, it should have occurred to you. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, לעולם, le'olam, really כראוי לשור ולא כראוי לגמל k'rauy l'shor
v'lo k'rauy l'gamal ושכיחי גמלים. u'shchichi gamalim. Really it was not responsible,
it was fit for oxen but not fit for camels and camels
were common. So essentially you could have expected it to break because
camels were common. ודקשיא לך, V'dekashya lach, you want to know פושע
הוא, poshea hu, isn't this obvious? If you did something that really
was negligent, so why does the משנה Mishnah have to tell you
you're חייב? chayav If it really was not a good covering, of
course you're חייב. chayav No, איידי דנסב רישא כסהו כראוי נסב סיפא
נמי לא כסהו כראוי. aidi d'nasav reisha kissahu k'rauy nasav seifa nami
lo kissahu k'rauy. You're right, it is obvious, but since the beginning
was telling you if you did a good job you're פטור, patur.
even if it rotted and something happened, the end of the משנה
Mishnah tells you if you did a bad job you're חייב, chayav
even though that's quite obvious because it was a clear case of
negligence.
Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, and okay, one minute, so let's just
stop. David, you had a question?
Is there any difference whether a person actually witnessed the camels walking
over?
Yeah, that would be, if the person witnessed the camels, that would
be like the case back in the משנה Mishnah. where the second
guy passes by and sees that it's uncovered. Then once you've seen
that and you have a reason to expect that that could have
weakened it, then you would become חייב. chayav. Okay, so that's a
discussion where the משנה Mishnah obviously doesn't prove any of it because
we're reading everything into the משנה. Mishnah And we don't know. איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, הא נמי ודאי לא איבעיא ליה. ha
nami vadai lo ibeiya lei. You know what? That was never a
question. דכיון דאתו לפרקים, De'keivan d'atu l'prakim, since camels occasionally come, פושע
הוא, poshea hu, you're clearly פושע. poshea. Obviously if it's something that
occurs with a reasonable likelihood, even if it's not right now in
front of you, even if it occurs once in the week, but
it still occurs once a week and so therefore how can you
say you're done with your responsibility? You know that the likelihood is
that once a week some camel will walk over this. Okay, that
makes sense. דאיבעי ליה אסקיה אדעתיה, Deibei lei askei adaiteih, it should
have occurred to you. Right, we don't say about oh you don't
have to start speculating. I guess part of the גמרא's Gemara question
here is, is that like it's not like everybody is a statistician.
People are common people. So the question is, obviously if we took
a step back and we said look, you're going to keep it
covered and think you're going to be exempt for the rest of
the week, but obviously camels, there will be a few camels that
will walk on it during the week. How could you say that
you've exempted yourself from your responsibility? So it seems the response is
דאיבעי ליה לסקיה אדעתיה, deibei lei l'askeia adaiteih, like how much can
we expect from the common person? A normal person who uses a
well, most people think about what they see immediately in front of
them. It doesn't, they don't stop to say one minute, it's actually
true that a few times during the week there are camels in
this רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. So even though from some like objective
perspective there was negligence because that is a reality that's going to
occur during the week, maybe it's not something we could realistically expect
for you to think about. That seems to be what the issue
of the גמרא Gemara was, maybe that partly also addresses my whole
question about the רוח מצויה ואינה מצויה. ruach metzuya v'einah metzuya. It's
not always an objective question of how much is the thing protected.
expected, it's what is it reasonable to demand for you to be
thinking about. And then the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, I'm
sorry, it's your well, you have to be thinking about those things
even if you, you know, you can't just say, well, I didn't
see any camels around. That becomes your responsibility to anticipate and think
about those things. So you are a פושע. poshea. We've, you know,
yes, though...
I have a billboard to put one of those signs, you know,
camel crossing.
Right, exactly. Okay. So if you decide to own a well, you
become responsible to think about what things might happen. Okay, so you
are a פושע. poshea. הוה ליה לאסוקי דעתיה, Hava lei le'asuki da'atei,
you should be thinking about it. מאי קא מיבעיא לן? Mai ka
mibaya lan? What was our question? הכי הוא דמיבעיא לן. Hachi hu
demibaya lan. This was the question. כיסוי כיסוי שיכול לעמוד בפני שוורים
ואינו יכול לעמוד בפני גמלים. Kisuy kisuy sheyachol la'amod bifnei shevarim ve'eino
yachol la'amod bifnei gemalim. It can withstand oxen, cannot withstand camels. ושכיחי
גמלים, U'shchichi gemalim, and camels are common. So you are clearly negligent.
You're not just negligent for camels, you're negligent for oxen, right? Because
you are putting in a place where you know that camels will
walk over it and weaken it. So you actually are putting on
a cover that is not even being responsible for the oxen that
walks or just romps on. But what happened? התליעה מתוכו. Hitliya mitocho.
It didn't get break because of the camels, it broke because it
because it rotted from within. It got termites from within, which you
had no reason to know about and to be responsible about. Okay,
so here is the question of, if you were negligent from one
direction, but something happened that caused it from a completely unrelated area
that caused it to break, do we still say that fundamentally you
were negligent regarding this בור, bor, or do we say no, what
actually happened in practice you were an אונס.
onnes, Okay, that's like you shoot an arrow into a guy and
he died of a heart attack a second before the arrow...
I don't know about that comparison, what it is similar to and
what this big תוספות Tosafot is about is a discussion about תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס. techilato bifshiya vesofo be'onnes. When you start out being
negligent about something and then something that happened that was that was
wasn't directly your act of negligence was an אונס, onnes, so that's
more what this is like and תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out
why this isn't that same conversation. Okay,
so that's the question.
מהו? Mahu? What? התליעה כאונס.
Hatla k'onnes. התליעה כאונס. Hatla k'onnes. Yeah, that's clear from the גמרא
Gemara from the very outset, that you know, that it's not considered
to have something that you could should be able to anticipate or
maybe even have a way of detecting. Okay, although the גמרא Gemara
will later talk about maybe you need to do regular inspections. Okay,
but at this stage we're considering התליעה אונס. hatla onnes. But do
we say look, it's not about the cover, it's about the בור.
bor. You were negligent about this בור. bor. And then in the
end something happened. That's the end, that's all I need to know.
Or do we say, no, the way it goes in, if you
directly look at did the person fall in as a result of
your negligence, he did not fall in as a result of my
negligence, right? Another way about looking about it is sort of like
a המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. We don't have to establish your negligence.
You dug the well, you're חייב. chayav. In order to get out
of the חיוב, chiyuv, you have to establish that you did a
sufficient שמירה. shemira. And as long as you can't say that you
did a sufficient שמירה, shemira, then you're just חייב chayav, for everything
because it's your well, right? So there's, you know, even if... so
it's not like a question of like, were you negligent for the
guy falling in, were you negligent for the cover breaking. It's like,
as long as you haven't done a כיסוהו כראוי, kisyuhu karauy, right,
then you're חייב chayav? regardless of what at the end of the
day is the reason somebody fell into it. All right, so anyway,
that's the question. The person fell in having nothing to do with
where your negligence laid in terms of the covering. Okay, so what
do we say? מהו? Mahu? מי אמרינן מיגו דהוי פושע אצל גמלים
הוי פושע נמי לענין התליעה, Mi amrinan migu dehavei poshea etzel gemalim
havei poshea nami le'inyan hatla'ah, because you were negligent regarding camels that
translates as negligence by the rotting. You've got real negligence but once
once you're negligent, you're liable, even though the rot even though the
rotting had nothing to do with your negligence, או דילמא, o dilma,
or do we say, לא אמרינן מיגו, lo amrinan migu, we don't
say because of this then that. We say at the end of
the day, no, if actually it broke having nothing to do with
your negligence, you're exempt. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. Now
again we're going to try to prove it from the משנה Mishnah.
where the משנה Mishnah. doesn't say any of this and we're going
to try to read it into the משנה. Mishnah
כיסוהו כראוי, Kisyuhu karauy, you covered it properly. ונפל לתוכו שור חמור
ומת פטור. Venafal letocho shor chamor vamet patur. Okay, and an animal
fell in and you're exempt. איתמר עלה, Itmar alah, it was said
on this. אמר רבי יצחק בר בר חנה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Bar Chana, שהתליעה מתוכו, shehitliya mitocho, it rotted from within. Now we're
going to question that statement. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case?
אילימא כראוי לשור וכראוי לגמלים, Ileima karauy lashor u'karauy lagemalim, it was
totally fit cover. ושהתליעה מתוכו vehitliya mitocho and it rotted from within.
פטור, patur. of course you're exempt. מה הוה ליה למעבד הרי אונס,
Mah hava lei leme'evad hare onnes, what could you have done, it
was an accident. What's the חידוש? chiddush? אלא לאו, Ela lav, if
there's a חידוש chiddush here and it's a case of rotting from
within, this must be the חידוש. chiddush. כראוי לשוורים ולא כראוי לגמלים,
Karauy leshvarim velo karauy lagemalim, that it was a proper cover for
oxen but not a proper cover for camels. ושכיחי גמלים U'shchichi gemalim
and the camels were prevalent. והתליעה מתוכו vehitliya mitocho and in the
end it rotted. So the חידוש chiddush is, even though the rotting
is an אונס, onnes. you might think you should be חייב chayav,
because of your negligence because of the camels, and that's not a
basis for making you חייב. chayav וקתני פטור, Vekatani patur, you're exempt.
אלמא, Alma, so the point of the משנה Mishnah would be saying
according to this, לא אמרינן מיגו דהוי פושע לענין גמלים הוי פושע
נמי לענין התליעה, lo amrinan migu dehavei poshea le'inyan gemalim havei poshea
nami le'inyan hatla'ah, that just because you're negligent for the camels, that
doesn't make you responsible for the rotting. At the end of the
day, the rotting is an אונס. ones, Okay, so if you say
the case in the case of rotting, to make it more of
a חידוש, chiddush, let's say it's this... case about the negligence for
the camels. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, no, you don't have
to introduce this negligence and the camels thing. לעולם כראוי לגמל ולא
ראוי לשור, l'olam k'ra'oi l'gamal v'lo ra'oi l'shor, it was completely fit
for all animals. ונתליעה מתוכה, v'nitli'ah mitochah, and it rotted, or I
keep on saying rotted, but the real point is that it was
termites. Okay, דקשיא לך כיון דנתליעה מאי הוה ליה למעבד, d'kashya lach
keivan d'nitli'ah mai hava lei l'me'avad, but your question is, I don't
get it, if it got wormy, that's what they say, if it
got wormy, what should you have done? Obviously you're an אונס, ones.
right? Why if there was... so what's the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה Mishnah if it was just that it got termites? No, maybe
that's not an
אונס. ones מהו דתימא איבעי ליה למיזל ולמנקש עליה, mahu d'teima ibayei
lei l'meizal u'l'menakesh aleih, you have to do regular inspections. You have
to come and you have to bang on it periodically to see
if it still like makes the right sound or is it indicating
that it's been, you know, eaten away from within side, hollow.
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you don't have to, which is a
good question, like why don't you have to? Right? But why do
you say it's ridiculous? Why?
Because you have to inspect.
I don't know. How often do you inspect your house for termites?
You know?
Excuse me? Like a house, a homeowner, like I'm prevented on everything.
Like I look at the roof, I look at...
you have to constantly...
alright, that's you. Alright, anyway, then we would have to figure out
what would be the...
then we would have to figure out how frequently. Once a year?
I mean if it was good solid wood, you know, but okay
fine. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. רוב כיסוי כראוי ונתליעה
מתוכה שור וחמור מת חייב. rov kisui k'ra'oi v'nitli'ah mitochah shor v'chamor
met chayav. The second part of the משנה. Mishnah Now we're going
to try to read all this into the second part of the
משנה. Mishnah Okay, that if it wasn't appropriate, you're חייב. chayav היכי
דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא לא כראוי לשור ולא כראוי
לגמל, eilima lo k'ra'oi l'shor v'lo k'ra'oi l'gamal, if it was obviously
not an appropriate cover, פשיטא למימר דחייב, pshita l'meimar d'chayav, you have
to tell me? Obviously, you know, you're negligent. אלא לאו, Ela lav,
so that the end of the משנה should be a חידוש, chiddush,
we must say the case is כראוי לשור ולא כראוי לגמל, k'ra'oi
l'shor v'lo k'ra'oi l'gamal, that it was fit for oxen and not
for camels. ושכיחי גמלים, v'shchichi gemalim, and if camels are common, פשיטא,
pshita, again, we're back to the obvious point that obviously you're חייב,
chayav it's obvious negligence. ואי לא שכיחי גמלים, v'ei lo shchichi gemalim,
and if they're not common, אונס הוא, ones hu, then obviously then
why should you be חייב? chayav, You're not negligent. אלא לאו דשכיחי
גמלים, Ela lav d'shchichi gemalim, it must be that camels are prevalent,
but so then...
but there's still a חידוש. chiddush. What's the חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש
chiddush is דשכיחי גמלים ונתליעה מתוכה, d'shchichi gemalim v'nitli'ah mitochah, that it
got wormy. וקתני חייב, v'katani chayav, so if it's telling you if
you didn't do it appropriately you're חייב, chayav for that to be
a חידוש, chiddush, let's say that's our case. Okay, that you were
negligent for camels and camels were prevalent, but in the end it
got wormy, and the חידוש chiddush is that that's considered not a
sufficient cover. אלמא מיגו דהוי פושע לענין גמלים הוי פושע לענין התלעה.
Alma migu d'havei poshei'a l'inyan gemalim havei poshei'a l'inyan hatla'ah. You see,
you say because you're חייב chayav for this, you should be חייב
chayav for that, once you were negligent, you're חייב chayav. across the
board. אמרי לא, amri lo, no, that's not necessarily what the משנה
is talking about. לעולם כראוי לשור ולא כראוי לגמל, l'olam k'ra'oi l'shor
v'lo k'ra'oi l'gamal, the משנה is talking about that it was fit
for oxen and not for camels. ושכיחי גמלים, v'shchichi gemalim, and camels
are common. ואתו גמלים וארעוה ואתו שור ונפלו בה, v'atu gemalim v'aru'ah
v'atu shor v'naflu bah, and the camels weakened it and the oxen
fell in. Okay, and then the whole thing is פשיטא, pshita, obvious,
because you were negligent, because you could have expected all of that.
ודקשיא לך פשיטא פושע הוא, v'd'kashya lach pshita poshei'a hu, you're saying
that's obvious, you're negligent. No, איידי דתנא רישא כיסהו כראוי תנא סיפא
נמי כיסהו שלא כראוי, aidi d'tana reisha kisahu k'ra'oi tana seifa nami
kisahu shelo k'ra'oi, because in the end we talked about a case
of a fit cover, we talked about a non-fit cover, but the
end of the משנה does not have to be a case of
a חידוש, chiddush, the very fact is you were just negligent and
that's why you're חייב, chayav. end of the story. So we do
not know yet the story that if you're negligent for one way
that it could break, if you're חייב for an אונס way in
which it broke. One minute, let's see, the גמרא is now going
to come to a conclusion and let's see how happy we are
with this conclusion. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. נפלו לתוכו
שור חרש שוטה וקטן, naflu l'tocho shor cheresh shoteh v'katan,
now we are going back to the... going to what the end
of the משנה was. An ox that is a חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh v'katan ox. Ox? Yeah, or...
I think the oxymoron, come on.
Oxymoron. I was... that was... I was waiting for that. I told
you, Dov's been waiting this whole מסכת masechet to use... to say
oxymoron. So I told Dov, when we talk about the ox that's
a שוטה, shoteh, you can talk about the oxymoron. Okay, so you
have an ox that's a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan, or
a סומא ומהלך בלילה, suma u'mehalech balailah, or the ox is blind
or it's nighttime. Why is all this true? Because the גמרא is
going to say, this is going to shock you, right? All this
whole time we've been talking about oxen, about all these exemptions for
the well, if a person dies, if a vessel breaks, the one
case that's חייב is if an ox falls in. The גמרא is
going to say, you know what? When that happens in the daytime,
you're פטור. patur? If the hole was exposed, because then the ox
should have seen it. Why is an ox walking into an open
hole? I mean, oxen look down and they look where they're going.
So the only way you're going to be חייב for your pit
is either if it was nighttime and the ox couldn't have seen
it, or the ox was blind, or the ox was a חרש
שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan, or I guess you did one of
those like, you know, fake covers that... what? It's weak.
It's a weak cover or it's a camouflage cover. Okay, so now
we're going to find out that a classic ox that falls in
a well in the daytime, you're
פטור. Alright, but if a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan ox,
or it's blind, or it's nighttime, חייב. פקח, Pikei'ach, if the ox
was a smart ox, okay, ומהלך ביום, u'mehalech bayom, and it was
a daytime... All right, now, ואמאי, v'amai, why are you פטור? נימא,
neimar, why don't we say, מדהוי פושע, mi'de'havei poshea,
since you were still negligent with this well for the oxen that
would fall in at nighttime, and the oxen that were blind, and
all these other oxen, so there was some general negligence still about
leaving this well exposed, so
הוי נמי פושע havei nami poshea for this type of a falling
in? So why do you get off? You weren't negligent here? You
have a well that wasn't covered, and that should be just an
across-the-board liability. Who cares that you weren't negligent when it was the
ox that was daytime and the ox could have seen it? Right,
why don't we just say, once there was some negligence here, you
have an across-the-board liability? So אלא שמע מינה ela shema mina לא
אמרינן מיגו, lo amrinan migo, you see you don't say מיגו, migo,
שמע מינה. shema mina. That's a good proof. Now, the problem with
this proof as תוספות Tosafot points out is, תוספות Tosafot says, this
has nothing to do with it! The reason that you are exempt
when an ox that, you know, if a normal ox... now I
always tell, I keep on telling you this story, right, about this
time that I went horseback riding and this person said to me,
like, we saw these guys on these dune buggies and he said
"I would never want to go on a dune buggy," I said
"why?", he said "a dune buggy can go off a cliff, a
horse is not going to go off a cliff." So, anyway, so
like, so if an ox normally is, doesn't fall into a well,
looks where it's going, and this ox did, it's not like you
say, "Oh, I wasn't negligent in that case." תוספות says what you
would say is, the ox did it to itself. Like, the idea
of a בור bor is that the בור bor made something, like,
you know, trip, right, it served as a hazard. Right, here you
would say, this was a stupid ox and it did it to
itself, it like committed suicide, like a normal, like, it sort of
used this בור bor to kill itself. Okay, you know, I'm serious,
that's what you would say if the ox was a smart ox.
It wasn't just that I wasn't negligent, it was that it was
מזיק mazik itself, my, my well wasn't the מזיק mazik of the
ox. That's very different when I did a cover that wouldn't have
worked for camels and then it rotted. At the end of the
day, it got exposed and some animal fell in and got hurt,
and that's classically what a בור bor does. So that's a case
where you can say "Well, maybe I wasn't negligent for this scenario,
I don't care if you were negligent for that scenario, you were
negligent in general." Okay, but it's very different than this case where
the ox actually, you know, is seen as like throwing itself in,
that's how we would think about it.
לא עכברא גנב אלא חורא גנב. lo achbara ganav ela chura ganav.
Something like that. Anyway, so תוספות says that this is a weak
comparison, but nevertheless the גמרא does come to this conclusion that we
do not say you have an across-the-board liability. You're only liable for
the scenarios you were negligent for, not for the ones that you
were not negligent for. But I have to tell you, in, in
my mind, the idea that you should be across-the-board liable makes a
lot of sense. It starts by being your well, it starts by
the fact that you're חייב. To get out of your liability, you
have to do a cover, a covering. If that covering was not
a fully responsible covering, right, we go back to... we don't say
"well, you were negligent for falling in this well," we go with
the fact that you're liable for the בור bor and until you
do a good cover, you remain liable. You don't think so?
No, it's just the opposite. The plaintiff always has the burden of
proof.
No, that's a burden of proof question, here we know what the
facts are.
But you have to prove that, that the person's negligence caused his
injury.
Right, but what I'm saying is, is that if it's, if the
negligence, if the narrative began with you didn't cover the well, then
it would be a question of: were your negligence of not covering
the well lead to this person's injury, this ox? But the narrative
doesn't begin there. It deals with digging the well. Then does that
create a strict liability of everything that happens in this well until
you have completely neutralized its danger? That, I see that there's a
good way of thinking about that. You've dug it, you have strict
liability until you've neutralized it.
Except if I can prove that you did not do enough inspection
and it was rotten. Right.
No, but that's when your lack of inspection is connected to what
happened. But here we're saying whether it's connected or not connected, can
we say you have strict liability until you've neutralized the danger?
So as opposed to...